Guide to the Lynne Sagalyn Research Files for "Power at Ground Zero" 1972-2016 MS 3128
New-York Historical Society
Lynne Sagalyn research files for "Power at Ground Zero"
1972-2016
New-York Historical Society
Sagalyn, Lynne B.
MS 3128
15 Linear feet in 13 record cartons + 1 oversize flat box
18 Gigabytes (2,743 digital files)
The collection includes the research files amassed by Lynne B. Sagalyn for her book "Power at Ground Zero: Politics, Money, and the Remaking of Lower Manhattan," published by Oxford University Press in 2016. Heavily represented in the collection are documents concerning the major institutional players in the redevelopment of the World Trade Center site, such as the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation, Silverstein Properties Inc. and other entities associated with developer Larry Silverstein, various levels of government, and others. Also with significant representation in the documents are those concerning the families of those killed on 9/11, cultural groups, civic organizations, urban and regional planning advocacy organizations, and others. The documents include a vast array of Board materials; contracts and other legal documents; arbitration and judicial decisions; presentations, testimony and other position statements; requests for proposals and responses to proposals; analyses, audits and other reviews and assessments; fact sheets, press releases, and other public relations and public engagement documents; economic assessments, project funding mechanisms, and other financial matters; news articles, architectural critiques, and other press and media coverage; and more. The collection also includes chronologies and other work product prepared by Sagalyn and her research assistants. The collection has both paper-based and digital components.
Arrangement
Aside from some minor shifts of a few folders, the organization of the paper files and their categorization remain as delivered by Lynne Sagalyn to N-YHS. The organization of the digital files remains as transmitted to N-YHS by Sagalyn.
Biographical / Historical
Lynne B. Sagalyn is the Earle W. Kazis and Benjamin Schore Professor Emerita of Real Estate at Columbia Business School, where she was formerly the director of the MBA Real Estate Program and the founding director of the Paul Milstein Center for Real Estate. An expert in real estate development and finance, Sagalyn has published extensively on a broad range of issues in the fields of urban development finance, public/private partnerships, and real estate finance. In addition to which, she has developed scores of cases for graduate-level teaching of real estate finance and investment strategy and been an innovator in curriculum for real estate study.
Sagalyn is widely known for her research on city building. Her book, Power at Ground Zero: Politics, Money, and the Rebuilding of Lower Manhattan (Oxford University Press), which is the subject of this collection, has received continuous praise and is regarded as the definitive account of that rebuilding challenge. Her earlier books on city building include Times Square Roulette: Remaking the City Icon (MIT Press, 2001), and, Downtown Inc.: How America Rebuilds Cities, co-authored (MIT Press, 1989).
Professor Sagalyn's activities outside academia are diverse. She currently (2021) serves on the board of Blackstone Mortgage Trust (NYSE: BXMT) and chairs its audit committee and the Advisory Board of Morgan Stanley PRIME Property Fund. In the not-for-profit realm, she is a member of the board of directors of the Regional Plan Association (RPA) and co-chairs its New York Committee, the Skyscraper Museum and serves as vice president, the board of the New York City Trust for Cultural Resources and chairs its audit committee. She has been a litigation expert, a consultant to both private firms and public agencies, and a member of the New York City [Board of Education] Chancellor's Commission on the Capital Plan. She has done extensive executive teaching, particularly for Tishman Speyer Properties and the Urban Land Institute.
In addition to her more than twenty years at Columbia Business School, Sagalyn has held appointments at the University of Pennsylvania in both the School of Design (City Planning Department) and the Wharton School (Real Estate Department), and at M.I.T., Department of Urban Studies and Planning, where she taught courses in public policy and real estate finance as part of the school's pioneering degree program in real estate development.
Professor Sagalyn received her Ph.D. from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a Master of City and Regional Planning from Rutgers University, and a B.S. with distinction from Cornell University.
[The above note was taken, with slight modification, from Sagalyn's biographical note on the website of Columbia Business School.]
Access Restrictions
The bulk of the collection is open to qualified researchers at New-York Historical Society. One box of documents (designated as Series XII. Restricted Files) is closed until 2039 as a condition of the donation.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lynne Sagalyn, February 2019. The paper files were received in March 2019. Digital files were received in February 2020 and May 2021.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes the research files amassed by Lynne Sagalyn for her book "Power at Ground Zero: Politics, Money, and the Remaking of Lower Manhattan," published by Oxford University Press in 2016. The documents include a vast array of Board meeting minutes and resolutions; contracts, agreements, leases, and other legal documents; arbitration and judicial decisions; remarks, presentations, speeches, testimony, and other position statements; requests for proposals, proposals, and responses to proposals; analyses, reports, performance audits, project status, and other reviews and assessments; fact sheets, press releases, publicity materials, and other public relations and public engagement documents; financial statements, annual reports, economic assessments, capital plans and budgets, project funding mechanisms, and other financial matters; news articles, editorials, opinion pieces, architectural critiques, and other press and media coverage; and more.
Heavily represented in the collection are documents concerning the major institutional players in the redevelopment of the World Trade Center site (WTC), such as the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey (PANYNJ), the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation (LMDC), Silverstein Properties Inc (SPI) and other entities associated with developer Larry Silverstein, and the World Trade Center Memorial Foundation. Also with significant representation in the documents are those concerning the families of those killed on 9/11, cultural groups, civic organizations, urban and regional planning advocacy organizations, and others. Government involvement from the city level to the state and federal level, including on matters of transportation, historic preservation, and economic revitalization, is also represented. In short, the collection includes all the documents underlying the multi-faceted complexities of rebuilding at the WTC site that Sagalyn harnessed in her writing of "Power at Ground Zero."
In addition to the source documents, the collection also holds chronologies, press logs, summaries, and other work product prepared by Sagalyn and her research assistants. The collection holds both Sagalyn's paper-based files and her digital files. There is overlap between these, in that some digital content was printed out and included in the paper files. But there is also much that is found in one place or the other because not all digital content was printed and, vice versa, not all printed material is in digital format. See the further note below for more information about specific primary source documents in the collection.
Bibliography for "Power at Ground Zero": Major Primary Sources
With her donation to N-YHS, Lynne Sagalyn provided a list of her major primary sources that goes beyond those included in the published book. Following is that list. Some of these can be found within the paper files though likely most others are in digital form. In either case the organization of the following list does not correspond precisely with the organization of the paper and digital files. The body of digital files can be searched using keywords from this list to find particular documents. It was not confirmed by the processing archivist as to whether or not all listed documents are in the collection.
Planning for Rebuilding
Government Actors:
* PANYNJ and LMDC, "Cooperation Agreement," May 10, 2002.
* LMDC, Principles and Revised Preliminary Blueprint for the Future of Lower Manhattan, June 5, 2002. A draft of this document was published April 9, 2002; after hearings were held, a Revised Blueprint was issued.
* PANYNJ and LMDC, "Agreement Regarding 7 World Trade Center Civic and Land Use Improvement Project – Condemnation Reimbursement and Award Agreement [Vesey Street strip of land]," April 1, 2002.
* LMDC and PANYNJ, "Request for Proposals to Provide Expert Professional Consultant Services Related to the Initial Phase of a Comprehensive Urban Planning and Transportation Study of the Downtown Manhattan Area with Special Emphasis on Development of the World Trade Center Site and Adjacent Areas," April 23, 2002. Related Document: LMDC reissuance, April 2002.
* LMDC and PANYNJ, Preliminary Urban Design Study, n.d [May 2002].
* LMDC and PANYNJ, "Future of World Trade Center Site, Adjacent Areas and Related Transportation Infrastructure: Public Input Process and Timeline," n.d. [May 2002].
* Letter to Lance Michaels from Kevin Rampe, Re: elements of cooperation between LMDC and DCP with respect to RFPS to be issued by LMDC in cooperation with the city," August 20, 2002.
* LMDC, Request for Qualifications, Innovative Design Study for the World Trade Center Site, August 19, 2002, including addendums.
* LMDC, "A Vision for Lower Manhattan: Context and Program for the Innovative Design Study," October 11, 2002.
* LMDC, "The Public Dialogue: Phase I (Preliminary Report)," October 24, 2002.
* City of NY Office of the Mayor, New York City's Vision for Lower Manhattan, December 2002.
* PANYNJ and LMDC, "Memorandum to Members, Joint Working Group, PANYNJ and LMDC, from Joseph J. Seymour and Louis R. Tomson, Subject: Reaching Agreement on an Integrated/Master Plan for the WTC Site," December 5, 2002.
* LMDC and PANYNJ, "The Public Dialogue: Innovative Design Study," February 27, 2003.
* Letter to John Whitehead from Larry Silverstein, Re: views of the Silverstein lessees on the planning process, January 31, 2003.
* LMDC, "Summary Report on the Selected Design for the World Trade Center Site," February 27, 2003. * Letter to John P. Cahill from Daniel L. Doctoroff, "Proposed Changes to New York State and New York City Roles in Lower Manhattan Rebuilding," n.d. [March 2003].
* LMDC, World Trade Center Site Memorial Competition Guidelines, April 2003.
* PANYNJ and LMDC, "Memorandum of Understanding" [regarding cooperation to implement the Studio Daniel Libeskind master plan], June 16, 2003.
* LMDC, Invitation to Cultural Institutions for the World Trade Center Site, June 30, 2003.
* LMDC, NYSDOT, MTA, NYC, and PANYNJ, Lower Manhattan Transportation Strategies, April 24, 2003.
* Letter to Joseph J. Seymour from Daniel L. Doctoroff [regarding master plan design for the World Trade Center Site], July 31, 2003.
* Letter to Joseph J. Seymour from Daniel L. Doctoroff, [regarding refined master plan for the World Trade Center Site that must be resolved for the City to approve the site's master plan], October 17, 2003.
* Letter to James T. Connors [PANYNJ] from James F. Risoleo [Host Marriott], "Re: New York Marriott World Trade Center [letter agreement for full settlement of Host Marriott's property claims to lease hotel]," October 21, 2003.
* FTA, FHWA, and LMDC, "Coordinated Determination of National Register Eligibility—World Trade Center Site, New York City, New York," March 31, 2004.
* Letter to John Whitehead and Kevin Rampe [LMDC] from City Planning Commissioner Amanda Burden, ACIP, [regarding review of the General Project Plan for the World Trade Center Site], March 8, 2004. Related document: "City Planning Commission Review of WTC Amended GPP [slide deck] (March 1, 2004).
* Letter to John Whitehead and Kevin Rampe [LMDC] from Amanda Burden [DCP], [regarding DCP review of the World Trade Center Memorial and Cultural Program, General Project Plan, dated September 16, 2003, March 8, 2004.
* Letter to Joseph Seymour and Kevin M. Rampe from Daniel L. Doctoroff, [regarding Proposed Redevelopment Agreement for the Redevelopment of the World Trade Center Site], April 5, 2004.
* LMDC, World Trade Center Memorial and Cultural Program, Record of Decision and Lead Agency Findings Statement, June 2004. Related document: Addendum to the Record of Decision (February 16, 2007).
* LMDC, World Trade Center Memorial and Redevelopment Plan, Final Generic Environmental Impact Statement, April 27, 2004. Related documents: "Draft Scope, World Trade Center Memorial and Redevelopment Plan, Generic Environmental Impact Statement," June 20, 2003; "Public Meeting, Draft Scope World Trade Center Memorial and Redevelopment Plan, Generic Environmental Impact Statement," Tribeca Performing Arts Center, Manhattan Community College, July 23, 2003; Final Scope for the GEIS, September 16, 2003; Draft GEIS, January 22, 2004.
* LMDC, World Trade Center Memorial and Cultural Program, General Project Plan, June 2, 2004, as amended February 14, 2007. Related documents: draft plan for the site (June 17, 2003), amended plan (September 16, 2003), proposed amendments (December 16, 2004), June 2, 2004 plan as amended May 19, 2005, proposed amendments November 9, 2006.
* PANYNJ and City of NY, "World Trade Center Redevelopment Agreement," including "Attachment A: World Trade Center Design and Site Agreement," November 24, 2004. Related documents: Restated and Amended Agreement between the City of NY and the PANYNJ, November 24, 2004 (the "PILOT Agreement"); Letter to City Hall from the PANYNJ, "Re: City Occupied Space, World Trade Center Site PILOT, November 16, 2006 and second letter to the City of NY from the PANYNJ laying out the details of the ownership of Cortlandt Street and Dey Street, November 16, 2006; PANYNJ, "Declaration of Restrictive Covenant, Block 58, Lot 1 (Cortlandt Street Right of Way, Dey Street Right of Way), December 5, 2007.
* LMDC, LMDC: Progress Report 2001-2004, December 2004.
* LMDC, Guiding the Process: The Public Dialogue and Lower Manhattan Revitalization Initiatives, April 2005.
* LMDC, "Overview of Public Comment on Draft Funding Allocation Framework and Revised Funding Allocation Framework," May 25, 2005.
* LMDC, Final Report, LMDC: 2001-2006, November 9, 2006.
* PANYNJ and City of NY, "World Trade Center Design Guidelines Administration Agreement," November 11, 2006.
* LMDC, "Environmental Assessment of the proposed World Trade Center Memorial and Cultural Program General Project Plan Amendments and LEED Gold Alternative Path to Achieve Goals of the Sustainable Design Guidelines," February 7, 2007.
* Studio Daniel Libeskind, "Memory Foundations, World Trade Center Commercial Design Guidelines, Final Draft" February 2007.
* New York Police Department, World Trade Center Campus Security Plan: Final Environmental Impact Statement, CEQR No. 12NYP001M, August 14, 2013.
Civic Groups:
* Civic Alliance, Listening to the City: Report of Proceedings February 2, 2002, South Street Seaport, Executive Summary, September 2002.
* Civic Alliance, "Towards a Planning Process for Lower Manhattan: A White Paper Prepared for the Civic Alliance, Revised Draft," August 28, 2002.
* Civic Alliance, Listening to the City: Report of Proceedings July 29-August 1, 2002, On-line Dialogue, September 2002. Related document: Participant Guide for the event.
* "Economic Development Working Groups Reports," prepared for the Civic Alliance by Alice Rivlin and Rosemary Scanlon, September 2002.
* Civic Alliance, A Planning Framework to Rebuild New York: A Report of the Civic Alliance to Rebuild Downtown New York, September 2002.
* Civic Alliance, Civic Alliance Planning Workshop, December 13-18 [actually 17], 2002, South Street Seaport, NYC. Related document: "Civic Alliance Planning and Design Workshop for Lower Manhattan, Executive Summary."
* Civic Alliance, "A Civic Assessment of the Lower Manhattan Planning Process: A Regional Planning Association Report to the Civic Alliance," October 2004.
* LCAN, "Labor Community Advocacy Network [LCAN] to Rebuild New York: Policy Statement," April 24, 2002.
* LCAN, Revitalize New York By Putting People to Work: A Jobs-Based Strategy for Economic Diversification and High-Road Growth, March 13, 2003.
* Municipal Art Society, "Imagine New York II: The People's Response, Preliminary Workshop Report," January 13, 2002.
* Municipal Art Society, Imagine NY: The People's Visions, Summary Report, June 20, 2002.
* Municipal Art Society, Imagine NY: Giving Voice to the People's Visions, December 2003.
* New York City Partnership and Chamber of Commerce, Working Together to Accelerate New York's Recovery: Economic Impact Analysis of the September 11th Attack on New York City, November 2002.
* New York New Visions, Principles for the Rebuilding of Lower Manhattan, February 2002.
* New York New Visions, "New York New Visions Lauds Winning Studio Libeskind Plan: A Promising Beginning, But Now the Work Begins," February 27, 2003.
* New York New Visions, "Possible Futures: Draft for Discussion," report of the Growth Strategies Team, May 2002.
* New York New Visions, "Statement Regarding Proposed Environmental Impact Statement on World Trade Center Site Design," August 1, 2003.
* New York New Visions, "Statement on Revised World Trade Center Plan," October 3, 2003.
* R. DOT, Towards a Sustainable City: Rebuilding Lower Manhattan, n.d.
Developing a WTC Memorial and Memorial Museum
* New York New Visions, Memorial Process Team Briefing Book: Findings from the Outreach, Temporary Memorials & Research Working Groups, March 2002.
* "The Memorial Process: A Report of the Lower Manhattan Rebuild Task Force, New York Metro Chapter, American Planning Association," Draft, May 14, 2002.
* LMDC, Memorial Research Tour October 1-5, 2002, slide deck.
* The Columbia Seminar on Art and Society, Department of Art History and Archeology, Columbia University, Monument and memory: essays by Daniel Libeskind, Leon Wieseltier, Sherwin Nuland, edited transcript of a program that took place at the New York Historical Society, September 27, 2002.
* LMDC Families Advisory Council, "Draft Memorial Mission Statement," November 8, 2002.
* LMDC, "Draft Memorial Mission Statement and Memorial Program," January 30, 2003.
* LMDC, The Public Dialogue Draft Memorial Mission Statement and Program for the World Trade Center Memorial, March 12, 2003.
* LMDC, "Memorial Mission Statement and Memorial Program," n.d. [April 10, 2003].
* LMDC, Transcripts of Joint Meeting of Memorial Competition Jury and Families Advisory Council, May 27, 2003, June 5, 2003.
* LMDC, World Trade Center Site Memorial Competition Guidelines, n.d. [April 2003].
* World Trade Center Memorial Jury, "Statement" delivered at the World Financial Center, New York City, for the announcement of the Eight Design Finalists, 19 November 2003.
* LMDC, "WTC Memorial Jury Statement for Winning Design," January 13, 2004.
* Michael Arad and Peter Walker, "Design Statement: Reflecting Absence," n.d.
* NYSHPO and LMDC, "World Trade Center Memorial and Redevelopment Plan Programmatic Agreement" [section 106], April 22, 2004.
* LMDC, "Public Dialogue Report on the Memorial Center Advisory Committee Draft Recommendations for the Memorial Center," July 19, 2004.
* LMDC Memorial Advisory Committee, "Recommendations for the Memorial Center," n.d. [2004].
* New York New Visions, "WTC Memorial Museum Programming Workshop," transcript of presentation given on September 15, 2005 at the Center for Architecture, NYC.
* Civic Alliance, World Trade Center Memorial Museum Programming Workshops: Summary of Proceedings, September 19 & October 11, 2005, n.d.
* LMDC, PANYNJ, and WTC Memorial Foundation, "Memorandum of Understanding" [regarding three-way exchange and transfer of property interests to accommodate redevelopment plan for the WTC site], February 1, 2006.
* LMDC, PANYNJ, and WTC Memorial Foundation, "World Trade Center Memorial/Cultural Construction Site Access Agreement," March 10, 2006.
* Coalition of 9/11 Families, Inc., et al, Plaintiffs, versus Kevin Rampe, President, LMDC, and The PANYNJ, Defendants, 04 Civ. 69941 (JSR) U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York, 2005 U.S. Dis. Lexis 1913, February 8, 2005 filed, February 8, 2005, Decided.
* Supreme Court of the State of New York, County of New York, In the Matter of the Application of the Coalition of 9/11 Families, Inc., et al, Petitioners, for Judgment Pursuant to Article 78 of the Civil Practice Laws and Rules, against the LMDC, PANYNJ, and Bernadette Castro, as Commissioner of NYS Office of Parks, Recreation, and Historic Preservation, Respondents, "Brief of Amici Curiae," April 20, 2006. Related document: Supreme Court of New York, New York County, 12 Misc. 3d 1173(A); 820 N.Y.S.2d 842; 2006 N.Y. Misc. Lexis 1626; 2006 NY Slip Op 51212(U); 235 N.Y.L.J. 99, May 11, 2006, Decided.
* WTC Memorial Foundation, "Confidential Memorandum [comprehensive snapshot of the status of the Memorial and Memorial Museum], May 2, 2006.
* Frank J. Sciame, "World Trade Center Memorial Draft Recommendations and Analysis," n.d. [June 20, 2006]
* PANYNJ, LMDC, WTC Memorial Foundation, City of NY, and State of NY, "World Trade Center Memorial/Cultural Project Agreement," July 6, 2006. Related document: PANYNJ, minutes of the board meeting, December 14, 2006 (322-325).
* National September 11 Memorial Museum at the WTC, Museum Planning Conversation Series Report 2006-2008, 2008-2009, Conversation Series Report, 2009-2010 Conversation Series Report, 2010-2011 Conversation Series Report, 2013 Conversation Series Report, all n.d.
* Letter to Christopher O. Ward, from family members, re: delay of completion schedule for the Memorial, July 10, 2008.
* National 9/11 Memorial and Memorial Museum at the WTC, 9/11 Memorial 2011 Year End Update, n.d.
* "The National September 11 Memorial Museum Davis Brody Bond Aedas Design Statement," n.d.
* PANYNJ and the National September 11 Memorial & Memorial Museum at the World Trade Center Foundation, Inc., "World Trade Center Temporary Operating License," September 9, 2011. Related document: First Amendment, September 6, 2013; Second Amendment, December 30, 2013.
* PANYNJ and WTC Memorial Foundation, "Memorandum of Understanding" [regarding memorial construction cost overruns], n.d. [announced September 10, 2012].
Protecting Historic Resources at the WTC Site Under Section 106 Process
* LMDC, "World Trade Center Memorial and Redevelopment Plan Proposed Finding of No Adverse Effect Under Section 106 of the National Historic Preservation Act," February 9, 2004.
* FTA, FHWA, and LMDC, "Coordinated Determination of National Register eligibility—World Trade Center Site, New York City, New York, March 31, 2004.
* LMDC, "Notice of Finding of No Significant Impact and Determination of Non-Significance, Proposed Refinements to the World Trade Center Memorial and Redevelopment Plan," April 4, 2005.